what's up peers and welcome to the
wasabi wallet 2.0 release party
uh we have been tinkering on some pretty
cool bitcoin technology over the last
two and a half years
and now finally
it's to a point where it's good enough
to release so we're quite excited a lot
of thoughts and a lot of research and a
lot of work
from quite many contributors
have been part of this software
development and
we're quite proud of what we've achieved
so today
a big chunk of the team is here for us
to celebrate that big monumental mind
stone to hopefully make that vision of
a monetary system that is not just sound
and hard and verifiable
but also private for everyday users by
default
and i think we've done some quite
substantial contributions to that vision
of frictionless and effortless privacy
by default for bitcoin
by solving a lot of these difficult
problems on the client side and that's
what wasabi wallet is all about
um so
maybe adam a couple words from you tell
us
why we're working on 2.0 and
what does what this technology means to
you
wow
where should i start
i have
created the first plans about wasabi
roller in 2015
christmas
eve
and
fast forward 3 years in 2018 we actually
launched the company and released wasabi
wallet 1.2
which was the bitcoin wallet that
enabled
privacy
on bitcoin for the first time for light
wallet users
the thing here is that enabling privacy
is not the same as
as as being able to use a wallet in just
in the same way
as any other bitcoin wallet would be
without privacy we want to have the
exact same user experience and
and also we will let user experience
were
quiet
advanced it was it was challenging
but
in
2020 we started
a research club
wasabi research club in january
and we started reviewing every single
bitcoin privacy research paper
up until that point and often even
interviewed the
the authors of the research papers and
you know when we've done our research on
bitcoin privacy and figured out how we
can do
better
on the privacy side
we also
started to completely rethink the user
experience of the
wallet
and and we actually ended up in a very
fortunate position
here which
you know i couldn't even dreamt of that
many ui developers are
maintainers of our ur framework are
working with us joined to us
on this on this mission for this cause
and you know no other software project
would even dream of having a single
maintainer of a ui framework let alone
two
or three years
many contributors to two maintainers and
they took this task of
of redesigning the complete ui
user interface of wasabi
reader with the goal
of actually
showcasing the ui framework that sabi is
written on
the template it's called avalonia but
wasabi 2.2 we reviewed over the privacy
research that there was and created our
own privacy referred called babisavi we
redesigned the user
experience and the user interface from
the ground up and we did not only
achieve our original way which is
that's built a privacy experience that
is exactly
as good as uh as any other bitcoin
bullet without privacy
but we actually achieved a much larger
goal which was that it actually the
single best
user experience for a bitcoin desktop
wallet that
what wasabi 2.2 has right now in my
number opinion
so
i hope that
we can
consider
bitcoins fungibility
fixed
in a very narrow sense
and
all we will have to do left in the
following
years
is to enable more and more type of users
and maybe even businesses to to to have
a fungible bitcoin user experience to to
use bitcoin privately and when we have
done that then the last thing what we
will have to do is fix bitcoin's
portability too so
then we will have uh have quite a ride
in the future to
to to try to make
make things cheaper and faster possibly
with probably with the lightning network
right so that's the
that's what i
i think
uh face
continue the show
very nice
david do you have any insights of the
last couple years
uh what are you excited about
yes so we are sitting here as you can
see in the
budapest headquarter office
basically this was
the center of
at least the budapest development here
[Music]
and a lot of things happened in the last
year
with the company itself
not just with the software
different kind of teams formed since we
begin because uh more and more
developers joined to the group
we have a marketing team as well beside
us
for example one graphical at least no
two graphical designer if i can say that
just to simplify things so we are
improving
the software in many other areas as well
like
is
is is the minimum required to have um
a comprehensive software
and all of these efforts are
forged into 2.0
you will see
the graphical interface is completely
changed and
tailor made to this specific purpose to
have a bitcoin wallet
the most recent features to send and to
receive
and
by the way meanwhile enabling the
privacy
by default for the user i think it will
be a very interesting journey for the
user as well how they will
get our user interface the the design
team try to make it as intuitive as
possible
sometime this was
hard to do because
we didn't want to have two tips there in
the software and a lot of texts
we said that or the motto was whenever
you need text to
to describe or to elaborate on something
that's not intuitive
so we again and again trying to find an
interface that we think it is
intuitively
working um it will turn out if we were
right or not now
so i'm
personally but i don't think i'm the
only one i'm very curious how they will
get this
because we were iterating a lot
on this kind of on these interfaces as
well
so that's about the ui
the coinjoin framework the new coinjoin
framework or coinjoin protocol
which is called bobby sobi
is
almost
opening a new dimension in the same way
as the ui changes in the software
for example one of the biggest uh
limitation for one point
for vb1 for wasabi that one was the 0.1
million denomination which was 400 at
the at the
beginning when we started wasabi wallet
but meanwhile it worked much more
thus uh
not letting
many users to use the wallet
so one thing was the that that ada
mentioned opera mentioned before
that uh
vasobi was for over users because there
were many advanced features the coin
list
cognitively hard to process
ui interfaces
it was like something like a logo for
a normal user but
2.0 tries to
tries to go over
on this for example we try to avoid
having a coil list in the software
because the coin list was the biggest
challenge as far as i noticed in wasabi
1.0 years
so we will try to
provide a better solution
we will see how it will turn out i think
we did what we could so
it's i i use the wallet confidently at
least during the test
i haven't seen any problem
with that
so
we can't say it's a new
it's a new era and uh
and and we did something
like uh
nobody asked if i could say that but not
in the manner that we are the first in
this but we are the first to experiment
with this how to have a wallet which is
privacy wallet but not having a coin
list inside it
it sounds
very good but
i think we were successful but let the
users tell us after the release so i i
am full with curiosity
how this will turn out we have been
working on this for two years so
it's a huge
it's a huge uh
effort
from our side how has he having positive
feelings right now so i hope i hope it
will be very good
and will be exciting for sure
there
you know we it kind of shifted the goal
post throughout the 2.0 development era
a bit and the the scope of the problem
that we were trying to tackle got bigger
and bigger and bigger um and to some
extent that's that's a bad thing right
because you you fellas waited well a
long time for a proper release with new
features
but on the other hand that allowed us to
really make a more holistic approach to
the big problem that's that's a big step
that's a difficult step
and i think we
we're doing quite well uh on many fronts
but you know as always the more you zoom
in uh there are numerous little problems
uh and things that can be improved uh
and that's for one
you know scary because the software
isn't perfect
however uh the the great thing is that
it still works and it works quite well
and we see all these low-hanging fruits
that we can improve in the future
and that will lead to well even the
greater software uh but what we have now
is
is really quite something it's
definitely a big improvement to
uh what we had in the past
and
yeah if this is the new status quo it
can only get better from now on then
i'm having a pretty bullish outlook on
the whole situation
so anyone any other notes before we
press that juicy big red button
just that the first
release of wasabi that was done
in
two years of
one person working on it and
one year of three other persons start
four other people started working on
that
this happened is three years and wasabi
2.2
was actually
another three years
after the initial inception of the the
the idea
two years and six months
but
it was
i think over 40 people were working on
that and
and many many many people here never
even experienced the wasabi at release
so that's uh it's an interesting font
i hope you guys are gonna like it
so there's another way to find out if
people like it other than to actually
ship the code so how about we do that
david are you ready
yes we are ready
from roll
also david the stage is yours
all right okay so we have this symbol
here
i can snipe the label
special table
i will press the button
and after that we start the deployment
which will take i think a minute and
then the software will be available so
shall i press the button guys
press the button
smash it
champagne
sunlight let the sunshine in and let
wasabi 2.2 in as well all right
it's there on github the website will be
refreshed soon
as well
we made it guys
could
that's it
yeah
okay i can't look at the website
yet
blue screen of death
next time what we need
is to order some
[Music]
some playing band to play live music in
the background for us
while we were waiting
[Music]
up and
down
the champion
all right
okay we are we are okay so um
you just download the software upgrade
it will upgrade the existing
installation and that's it
yes it should be as straightforward as
any other update that you did to wasabi
wallet if you're running an old client
uh you will get a little notification at
the bottom status bar saying that a new
update is available click that link
it'll show you the beautiful new website
and there download the package for
whatever platform you are running by the
way apple m1 silicon is natively
supported so if you have that get that
dedicated package
and well you install it and all your
existing wallets
will continue to work just as fine
and they
there's no need to import again if you
were using wasabi before
the the import should be rather quick
and
then you can use wasabi 2.0 with your
existing wallet of course alternatively
create a new wallet
make sure you've got your backup
recovery words
uh and then receive some bitcoin into
that wallet uh and press play in the
altercoin join
it'll ask you what type of mode you want
if you prefer to optimize for privacy
for cost or for speed
uh you just check uh whichever is the
right one for you and that's basically
it you wait a couple hours and then you
can spend your bitcoin privately by
default hopefully a couple of hours
right but what if
is there any way that we are not going
to make coin joints in the next couple
of hours would that be possible sure i
mean for one the biggest question is
are our users going to download the
software
uh
and well hopefully they are
and if yes then hopefully they they
send bitcoin into their wallets and then
hopefully they press play in the
altercoin joint
and if all these things check out then
we should have at least sufficient user
base to have hopefully quite large coin
joints
then the next big question is will the
server and the client software hold up
the stress test of potentially hundreds
of users coming online
and will we you know not have some
uh basically denial of servers uh that
that might be one possibility uh just
too many users
i guess there will be a good problem to
have and then uh it gets into optimizing
the code um but we will see that i'm
confident that we'll see something nice
on midnight
quite soon
is someone watching the back end logs to
see if there's any uh successful punjab
coordination going on maybe someone has
a counter of the current uh registered
input number
we can take a look at it yes
adam can you
check the look
on the back end
i think we won't have an ex counter
there
and uh like their input registration
timeout is one hour by minimum so 150.
one other thing is we have the
stats.wasabi wallet.io
which shows you the current download
numbers
of our github packages um
but
i checked just now and unfortunately
there is nothing on the
2.0 release yet so i'm guessing we might
have a way to have to wait a bit before
that is registered and indexed the first
data will be on the midnight
but max there are other sites those
where you can check the download
it's just not that fancy what we have
let me check that for you
20 20 downloads
okay
so let's maybe talk a bit about the the
features of this new coinjoin protocol
that we have rave uh could you maybe
give a short summary uh of all the
features
that are specific to the conjoint
um
i don't know it's really hard to try to
even think of all of them but i think
like the
biggest thing
is that we have not we don't have that
kind of minimum denomination anymore
that we have in 1.0
so people with less than 0.1 bitcoin are
actually able to reclaim their privacy
now and even the people with much larger
amount than 0.1 are able to do it much
more efficiently with 2.0 uh overall
like yeah the whole point joint protocol
is completely different input
input input links or input output links
or output output links yeah um overall
like i think we still have a lot of work
to do but this is a very very nice first
release and it should be like a big big
improvement for bitcoin privacy in
general yeah you guys might want to dive
deeper into those yeah so again the
minimum denomination now is five
thousand cents uh plus whatever the
mining fee is uh which is quite nice so
that means uh you can make
small value private payments
uh easily uh and then uh coinjoin the
change uh or uh make sure that you
well just have a few coins that are
exactly the size that you need them uh
there's no longer the need that every
user has a 0.1 coin at least
there's now much much more
possibilities of which denominations you
can choose in a certain round
and a lot of randomness of for example
how many inputs are you going to select
or how many outputs are you going to
select and all of this of course works
nicely by default and with our auto coin
join robot and that self driving car
that hopefully is not going to make many
crashes but that means that a lot of the
advanced decisions don't happen under
the hood which is quite nice
and i think the analogy of self-driving
car is actually pretty fitting in here
it's a very interesting technology and
you only
like there's only a certain limit that
you can test a self-driving car in a
test environment at some point you just
have to put it into an actual street and
hope that there's
well not many casualties i think
it's a very like
interesting technology and i think it's
the future but you know these first
steps these are going to be very
interesting and this is like you know
making history maybe jumar can you give
some more insights in the ui what are
some of the cool new features that you
implemented hey guys so yeah i'm
compared to 1.0
i mean aesthetically
um
speaking you know it looks a bit more a
bit more better
um the wallet selection as well is um
much better
and
we are using a coherent um design
language across the app now
so
i think that will also help in the user
experience as well
and we've rounded corners now
it looks very slick oh yes i'm using a
great grip
amount of um
blur behinds
rounded corners you know just to have
that um modern look across all platforms
that we support one of the other cool
small ui changes are things like small
animations uh which seem to be much
smoother uh so maybe tomorrow how does
avalonia handle these animations why
does it look so good
we are building at the um
the foundations we have laid years ago
for animations you know in upcoming
avalonia release also
that will
get better with them better
apis render threads um animations and
stuff and also um we also
uh base some animations from
microsoft's uh
design you know so
we had that um a bit more professional
touch now than we had in one point
though and it's really well i'm not sure
if it's really great if we get more and
more like microsoft
but probably it is uh their design is
quite nice um and definitely what what
is the wasabi looks awesome when it
comes to design i mean the top tech
firms really has it on the game you know
it doesn't get much better than that
sadly well until now because
we saw all right wasabi 2.0 over tops
them all oh yes definitely
lucas maybe you can give a quick update
what were you tinkering on what are you
excited about in this release um i'm i'm
interesting on seeing how it works in in
under
stress that's something that it's it's
what i want to to see basically i'm
excited about the the technical part
i would like to see a a huge transaction
i i mean we have been testing and we
know it it can work with you know 100
inputs and it can generate hundreds of
outputs but
um i think
it can do much better than that and
we need more users
i mean more users participating we need
people to migrate from whatsapp wallet
one i mean to the zerolink protocol to
the quality protocol
and well that would be will be something
really cool to see yeah definitely what
are your bets that the this back-end
server is gonna run too hot with all the
fancy crypto that's going on
i don't think so in fact even even in
the even in the worst uh because given
the remix is is free let's say
you don't pay for remixes
so in terms of input
cryptography
is
you or of the protocol in general is
that you register each input under a
separate tor identity
um and uh with just a single input right
and if you want to register multiple
inputs you create a new tor identity and
register it with the coordinator there
thanks to the new arbitrary amount ecash
system that we're using in wabi-sabi
this is no longer an issue that makes it
possible in cryptographic layer and on
the tor protocol here
and then we have a a plus saw
distribution of the timing of when you
register an output sorry in input what's
kind of the same for outputs too
and um
so
there there is randomness in the timing
as well
and then in terms of which inputs are
going to be selected uh a couple
checks uh in terms of what annon score
do the inputs have
and which amounts do they have
and especially um
so when we choose a group of possible or
potential inputs we check how many of
these inputs come from the same previous
transaction
which of course reveals at least to some
extent a common ownership input or input
ownership and assuming that this is
quite a large number
um it will become more difficult to find
out which of any given inputs actually
belong to the same user
and so here of course assuming there is
natural anonymity set in terms of real
users
um this calculation gets more difficult
the exact extent of how difficult it is
to find the input clusters now is yeah
difficult to say but i believe it's
quite all right how is that being
measured
um
i i was thinking maybe
avi should actually reply to this
this concern because
he's actually
i'm somewhere on the middle but he's
actually in a complete opposite uh
i mean coming at it from a concrete
opposite way so so that should be
interesting what he has to say about
this was researching it
i'll get back to my apartment in five
minutes and uh i'll address the question
then so i i guess i just did
the short version of it of how i think
about it
is that with
also between point of in the beginning
we were
we were trying to find an amount
composition scoring system
in a way that we can actually somehow
work with number of subsets
trying to maximize subsets of the of the
coinjoin or even better trying to
minimize the probability links between
input inputs
any specific input and any specific
output
and any specific output on any specific
input at the beginning we are trying to
to go into this direction because
obviously this is the most complete
solution that you can have for the
amount organization program and we did
not actually
well i wouldn't some people
think that we did find solutions to that
but
we were not
convinced that those things are work and
they were very risky so what we
defaulted back to is equal outputs and
what it results in it still creates a
bunch of subsets but if we see an equal
output
then we can be at least sure that there
is
ambiguity there even if there are
changes in the transaction or more like
unequal outputs these are not changes
anymore even unequal outputs cannot be
followed back but we are less sure about
that
therefore it is not included in our
anonymity calculations we only care
about equal outputs so this this would
be my short version
short rationally
and and
another thing to consider is we since we
have standard denominations across
multiple rounds now
that means that
it often happens that on the input side
users by random chance select inputs
that have equal amounts than other users
and this is kind of a mixing on the
input side it's not really designed or
optimized for this it just happens as a
side product but that definitely
increases input side privacy as well
again but you know to measure and
express that exactly i guess a bit tough
oh and another thing to consider is when
when we consolidate inputs uh in a coin
join um then we take the weighted
average for the anonymity score um so
let's say you two you have a a large
value coin with 10 and on score and then
a low value coin with three and on score
for example then your average weighted
and on score would be higher uh um
because the large value coin has more
announced for and then this would be
then the base set where the output side
and on score gets added to which then
depends on the number of equal amount
outputs maybe by now aviv is in the
house no guys i'm i'm two more minutes
away i apologize
no worries at all we should do a
different question and then we'll come
back to it as well
yeah i was actually trying to give
questions to max uh before we come back
to it well since then wrote up that you
become the ceo of wasabi wallet or zp
snacks
this
current stream is the first time you are
actually appearing as the ceo ck snacks
so how does that make you feel
yeah quite i'm quite excited about it to
be honest i mean i love wasabi as a
software project i always have uh and
it's it's mission and vision behind it
uh and i've been a user of the client
for a long time and based on that an
enthusiast contributor to the project uh
and now
being on the user side of the back end
uh i i guess i can lift that ethos
and double down on it and i will
try to give good feedback to the
software project in terms of
back-end functionality and yeah we'll
we'll hope that ck snacks as a company
will continue to not just
provide incredibly valuable services to
its users and but also to continue its
well i guess philanthropic
uh contributions to the free and open
source software space i think we're
already doing some quite amazing work
there but
we can do much more uh so i'm hoping
that ck snacks will be
yeah more more involved in in other
software projects
and and that
wasabi will continues to be
resilient and and feature rich and uh
just working well um but to a large
extent you know it's it's business as
usual i loved the project before i love
it as much or more now
and
i'll just try my best to build something
that's useful
and i think we have one of the best
teams to make that happen even though
it's a incredibly ambitious and
difficult problem to tackle so i'm
definitely not too confident
but i am hopeful and optimistic can you
maybe give an account of
yourself who are you how did you get to
study where were you before and and what
did you hear
so
a bit of a history lesson please
yeah um
so i'm mainly i would say an
entrepreneur and economist
right before bitcoin
it was always important for me to earn
my earn money first and foremost right
but then coincidentally you realize that
all that means you got to be useful for
other people
and that was always something that i
found quite enjoyable i then discovered
economics as well the the science to
become a better problem solver and
entrepreneur and
thereafter first trying out the
keynesian mainstream nonsense i
thankfully discovered the austrian
school of economics and
that
helped me a lot with understanding the
the role and the tasks of entrepreneurs
and the importance of money and so then
after studying this i
learned about the problems that the fiat
money has
and
i was eager to find a solution to it and
that led me to bitcoin ultimately as a
money that is defined verifies and
enforced by the merchants that use the
money system
and that's such a genius idea that
solves so many problems uh and if the
software is so elegantly designed uh
that it's caught my attention quite
quick and the fault on the bitcoin
rabbit hole was
was steep
and and harsh um but i've enjoyed every
minute of it uh and then wasabi wallet
uh i discovered back when it was hidden
wallet i believe in the end of 2017 uh
based on nopara being part of the block
digest a phenomenal podcast and there he
was talking about the development
process and
i thought to try it out alofty loved the
idea
so
stuck around and figured out that it's
pretty bad
despite how cool it is
and there were like a thousand and one
things to to improve that were so
obvious uh so i stuck around had
conversations with the other
contributors and added some educational
videos of how to use it
eventually answered a bunch of questions
from other users then got lazy doing
that
so i wrote the documentation that i
don't have to repeat myself that much
and a bunch of others helped out with
making that happen yeah then got more
into let's say the technical side you
know reviewing a lot of the pull
requests testing the software giving the
feedback um what's broken what could be
better
and
then as well the the research side you
know really thinking deep about the
architecture and the design of the
software about the different tricks that
can be used to make it more private
efficient uh useful yeah i guess all of
that
led me here to this point now um where
i'm kind of just planning to continue
doing what i do and double down on this
well open source ethos of scratchy
ownage you know we're building
software tools that
anyone else can use when we make it
better it's better for everyone else
that's such a massive improvement in
all resource allocation and and wealth
that we're creating here so
uh yeah i'm i'm in it for the mission
and
don't plan on stopping anytime soon
all right thank you let's get back to
aviv then so what are your thoughts on
input input links uh before i get there
uh so firstly a big congratulations to
uh to max um i i can only imagine how um
how uh a big of a dream this this is uh
for you because i i know max has always
been incredibly passionate about this
project um for first
almost since the beginning although
technically the beginning was in 2013 or
even 2015 but um he's been in this for
for
a very very long time the second thing
is is that i just wanted to get to dan
to maybe articulate more of his concerns
you kind of mentioned a couple of things
about timing attack coordinator and i
just wanted you to kind of elaborate on
precisely the the attack that you're
concerned
about so like if i make a payment
how do i make a payment through with
wasabi without making a link to my past
history my concern is if i make two
payments unrelated identities
and then later change from those
payments gets coinjoined the change from
those two payments is still related
in the
coin join that they're both input to
that both to change transactions are
input to linking them even though
the input and the output are not linked
yeah absolutely that that's that that's
a great uh question there so there will
be instances where you do have a wallet
with just two change payments and it may
it may be the case that the wallet
chooses to select both of those inputs
to mix in other situations you can
imagine where the wallet might have a
lot of partially mixed coins or fully
mixed coins and i've already spoken
about this and i think in the future
we'll want to have a system where we we
we combine inputs of already mixed coins
with those change coins but the the
bigger question that you're probably
asking is what is the link ability like
i guess you know mathematically that
i mean if the two appear in the same
coin joins there's inevitably a link in
that they both appear in that coin join
um so you know there's no way to get rid
of that
that's not entirely true though like
there's a link in that they're both in
the same coin join but the probability
that
two related inputs could go to any
outputs is not necessarily the same
across all all inputs and it's possible
that only one sub transaction fulfills a
certain subset of outputs and then you
still have a you don't have a
deterministic link between inputs and
outputs but you still have input input
links i i don't see that mitigated it's
a concern of mine not just for train
change coins but for any inputs i'm
wondering how that's being mitigated
well
yes
just as one small note that once you
make a payment the change output has a
one and on score
and and uh the input selector prefers uh
to have a low count of consolidation of
one anon score i'm not exactly sure
about the details of that algorithm uh
but we already tried to reduce uh the
consolidation of one and on score coins
but so you even served a one two
four with a coin joint output there
could be a you could make a
deterministic link between those two on
the input side i'm not like is is
so so
let's just you're not trying to merge
the two in the same input so there are
several questions here one question is
if you have two inputs that are from two
um
you know transactions where you um you
you have two change amounts and they
both have some link to your identity and
now you want to mix them and they're
mixed together do those two inputs have
a link you know again you can you can
you know i would say that for for large
transactions the kind that we kind of
expect the link is is very modest and
we've looked at at the numbers you know
for any amount any any doesn't matter
what amount of of bitcoin that you have
on the left-hand side there's you know
typically thousands of ways that it can
be represented as a valid amount on the
right-hand side in the form of five six
seven you know eight outputs if if you
have you know our expectation is
something like two to three hundred
inputs and two to three hundred outputs
per coin join you know even if you could
hypothetically break down all the valid
sub transactions which we don't we don't
think is is feasible you know barring
some
you know crazy uh you know someone being
um you know half the clients or or a
majority of the clients
um why don't you think that's feasible
to to break down the subtract the valid
sub transactions in a 200 input 200
output coinjoin
yeah it's just the the the time that it
would take is is immense
computationally too hard is the
assumption and and it's in particular
because we have like you know so many
denominations and and that users only
choose you know specific denominations
it might it might have been a different
thing if we said you know users are just
deciding their own denominations and
they're not cooperating and then there
could be some
link but again every user regardless of
the amount of bitcoin they have will
have thousands of ways to represent
their particular amount of bitcoin
whether it's one input or 10 inputs
which is the limit up to 10 inputs
they'll have thousands of ways to
represent that as outputs and so and
that's for every coordinator side where
there's like a minimum threshold of
thousands uh no so it's it's it's it's
uh we we know based on the amount of
bitcoin they have so this this number
goes radically down if the amount is
really really small so if someone shows
up with 50 000 satoshi's then yes
there's almost no ways they could they
could represent that on the output side
but the moment you hit more than like i
think it's like 10 millibit coins or you
know 50 million bitcoins a very small
and reasonable amount then the number
quickly grows and then it starts to
decay as as you go past like one one
bitcoin amounts um
depending on and again this also depends
on on the users and and how large their
coins are but yes uh we've we've looked
at this and there are in fact thousands
of ways to represent uh your input like
99 of input amounts as uh in eight coins
you know five six seven or eight coins
on the right hand side yeah my question
my question isn't asking about the
right-hand side my question is about the
probability that one input is related to
another so let's walk through that right
so how would you uh so the way that you
would um
you would figure out that input you know
7 and input 12 are linked is that you
take all the inputs and you take all the
outputs and you break it down into sub
transactions valid sub transactions
right and you say i've noticed that
input 7 and input 15 or whatever i just
said i already forgot are always
together
right that's how you find out that input
7 and input 15 are linked is that
they're always together when we break
into sub transactions but i'm telling
you that um and and this goes in the
reverse order as well right you could
have eight inputs
so
you can't exclude that from the table as
well and you know i've been i've been
saying this in the research clubs that
you know it's critical that we have coin
joins where individuals have you know
more than eight inputs and and ideally
eight outputs as well precisely for this
reason you're gonna have a lot of you're
gonna have a lot more than one way to
represent uh input seven and input 15.
you know you're gonna have sub
transactions where they're separate
you're gonna have the subject sub
transactions where they're they're uh
with other coins entirely um you're not
it's not going to be completely without
a link we we know that you know
everything is linked to everything
there's some
with with exceptions almost any coin
could be associated with any other coin
in to some degree when when the coin
joint is large enough because there are
just so many coins to choose from and
there's so many ways you can construct
uh but this is what i think about so if
you wanna if you want to talk more about
this i would love to have you join the
wasabi research club or just just uh you
know schedule time and we can we can
talk uh about this um is is that the uh
only concern because that doesn't sound
like the the coordinator uh concern i'm
still not sure how it's addressed is
there some like minimum
set is there a minimum number of
participants for the coin join you
enforce or is it
yes
can i give it a try and you guys uh
fix it if i say something wrong sure
okay so we either have a coinjoin round
going through every hour or when there's
150 inputs i think currently it's not
every hour so the minimum is 150 inputs
that we're targeting let's say let's
assume that so if you have 150 inputs
even if the two of them are yours it's
very very unlikely that you're going to
be able to link them those two together
and like any
reasonable probability how unlikely what
probability it it varies it it
varies on the situation it's a minimum
threshold that's what i'm asking like
or is it just
i should trust you technically the
server has a maximum number of inputs
which triggers around all the time so as
soon as we hit the maximum number the
coin john bond gets triggered right or
if we hit the one hour mark that's the
timeout card constrained right that's
kind of similar to how we had it in 1.0
either 100 users the heart limit upper
limit or the one hour time node and just
now the coordinator no longer knows the
number of users
because he doesn't know input input
linkage and therefore its numbers of
inputs which is currently at 300
and we have a minimum
a minimum input count multiplier i guess
in the in the configuration and that is
currently on main net set to 0.5 so with
this means we have 300 maximum and the
minimum is 50 of that meaning 150. so if
after one hour and still there are not
150 coin joints inputs registered to the
current round of coin join then this
will fail and we start another input
registration for another hour i believe
yeah and a few things to note over here
we have whale pools so if you have a
really big amount you're gonna probably
wait few rounds so you're not you you
actually like mix with the other big
whales
so that's one thing then the other thing
is that you're choosing
between one to eight inputs into your
coin join so it's very like even
oh yeah one to ten so even if you know
that you know these two inputs belong
together for some weird reason
you still wouldn't be able to you know
like that's let's say you get to change
out from me uh and you put these two
into coinjoin round i still don't know
if you have registered even more inputs
in there and also if you have a change
output it probably has the annual score
one so you're probably not consolidating
these two coins together at this point
but you're actually
like decomposing them
but either way it's
it's very very unlikely that you're
gonna figure out uh these links
uh d dan um so i i i love your your
skepticism because this is how i uh
approach things and and thank you for
once again letting a meeting that i'm a
part of be hijacked into a wasabi
research club that's kind of my goal
here every meeting is a wasabi research
club when i'm in the meeting but um
so one solution is that you don't
perform coin joins with uh with coins
with an onset one with more than one
coin um uh uh and an even better thing
would be you perform uh them with maybe
one coin that's that's your change coin
and then if you have any already mixed
coins or almost mixed coins you can you
can begin mixing that coin with those
coins as well
because those coins are unlinked you
know in inputs are not linked by the
coordinator because of uh of the
wabi-sabi protocol and so now it becomes
even harder
because now when someone's is following
your change amount
right they're not going to be able to
reasonably know where that money went
in on the right-hand side because you've
paired a bunch of more anonymous coins
on the left-hand side with the the the
change so would that be um one one
solution
i i understand more now
i'm i'm still i'm going to have to read
i suppose um
yeah it's not easy
the solution i just told is i was just
told this don't coin join with anon set
one coins but that's where everyone
starts so
no no no sorry what i'm saying is that
this is the surefire 100 solution
whereas normally it would still
you know be not very linkable we just
cannot tell you exactly the number
and and there are edge cases where those
two coins could have a very strong link
like 95 percent or even 100 percent i
like i'm not saying it's broken if if if
you don't do this method it's just it it
it's about how extreme you want to go in
terms of
um
in terms of like the certainty and just
to clarify before speaking about uh
prefer not to consolidate
more than one coin with one anon score
when you register your inputs for
coinjoin uh and again this check is
happening i'm not sure exactly again
about the details but another
observation here is that if we have a
kind of deterministic protocol of things
like input or output selection then this
someone decreases the ambiguity of the
round right for example if the adversary
knows that any client always only
registers a single one and on score
change coin if if that's how the client
behaves all the time 100 of the time
then if the adversary looks at a coin
join and he sees a single
uh non-standard change
input
then
he will know that this is the only
non-standard change input of this user's
input cluster right because the client
never selects more than one like that
and and so he this decreases the
ambiguity of what's the input group of
any of that particular user and then
that's why in general i believe it makes
sense to have some randomness here right
so that you you don't say we always only
pick only one anon score coin
but
you know sometimes occasionally even
pick two or three and this all in all i
think increases the ambiguity because
now an outside observer who only sees
the input and output list of that
coinjoin has a much harder time to try
to fingerprint what is the behavior of
one given user
i agree let me let me summarize this
which is how i think about it i i wrote
an article called privacy guarantees of
wasabi at 2.2 then i asked the question
what are the privacy guarantees
firstly there is a computational
hardness in the anonymizing wasabi
wallet
but
probably that computational hardness of
quantum computers improve or whatever
happens in a hundred year is going to be
broken but there is a second line of
defense which is the
the
subset number of subset transactions and
more
importantly
the input
inputs and outputs and outputs and
output so there are privacy hard privacy
guarantees there but what's the problem
with that well the problem with that is
that we don't
know exactly
what a specific case of of coinjoin
resulted in and finally this is why we
are going
doing equal outputs
because that's the third line of defense
equal outputs which by the way people at
1.2 that was the only line of defense
right the third line of defense is the
equal outputs right so
that is being proven to work in vasa
people at 1.2 but again there are those
other two things which i know uh you
guys find the second one very very
uh exciting and i guess the thief give
you back the bird max
thanks for your summary adam
if i can just add one more thing there's
like 15 additional problems that
we we've been looking at and discussing
uh you know i'm i'm personally very open
to hearing those problems and like
thinking about them i'm not sure how
familiar with those other problems uh
and if you've been sort of following the
the wasabi research club but i i really
encourage you to um to kind of be you
know be a part of that conversation so
we can uh can make progress yeah
definitely again this is a really really
difficult problem what we have is i
think well thought through and quite all
right
but again it's definitely not perfect
there's rooms of improvements a lot
uh and yeah getting feedback on things
like this is very important so much
appreciated then yeah overall this is a
very good question and
like
you saw now it's not really easy to
explain this
so we still have
a lot of work to do on making that more
efficient anything else then any other
feedback
the other thing i
heard that got brought up was that you
can modify the client not to pay any fee
that's not enforced is that actually the
case
i hate to ask a yes no question but
that's uh
that one that one stuck out to me
yeah that was no about it but
it did not end up being the case
the answer is it's no
basically um but if
yes no
you cannot
i know what you mean is basically what
you can do if you don't want to pay a
coordination fees
split your coins under the
what we call the
pleb the
threshold right
so you can if you participate with very
small coins you are not going to pay
of course you are going to pay more in
in
network fees because
you will need more participate in more
rounds with more coins in order to
achieve the same level of privacy right
so you can you can do that that is what
nothing much was um talking about in
fact he he clarified that
you know in a tweet uh but i would like
to
if that is okay i would like to answer
your project your previous question if
it is good because basically
it is basically how to guarantee if you
want that inputs to input
links are not let's say easy to to see
right or to to discover or to analyze
first of all
we have to in order to see how good
quasavi wallet 2 is we can compare it
with
the other and
coinjoin protocols for example if you
have for example
the summary one well in summary wallet
you have to reveal
your
wallet your coins in a transaction zero
or initial transaction so so everybody
that can read the blockchain or can use
a blockchain explorer can see
those inputs right
something similar but but
better happens with
um joy market
because in joy market one input belong
to one of the the maker or the taker
right
if it is the first first round right so
you know the input that comes from a
previous joint market coin joint
is the taker right and and the new money
is the is the maker right so you you can
know
sometimes
the common ownership of the invoice in
what's required one only the coordinator
can know that because all the inputs
goes together in one single
http request to the coordinator so the
coordinator can know that but nobody
else can in what's having quality 2
no one can know that even the
coordinator doesn't know that right
because all the inputs are
registered
with a different identity so
basically in in that specific
area what's happening wallet 2 or what
we
is the best of the best of the best of
the product
right
the thing is that
of course we want
more and better and better and better
and better technology so that's why we
are asking these questions but in terms
of
that there is nothing like uh
wabi-sabi product then we can discuss if
you want
if
those links can be analyzed
once they are
available on the blockchain
well it's another discussion that of
course the answer is
is not
because that is basically the service
that we are providing right the linking
of
the coping inputs and output basically
that is our business well that's that's
my concern is i i don't believe that's
true right now the input input links the
claim that the input input links could
only be identified by the coordinator in
the past and now can't because they're
registered across different requests is
just not the case given either as aviv
was saying sufficient computation across
a whole coin join to find all of the
possibilities or if you were to
uh if you were to make that comp
computation more efficient in a targeted
attack if you had some idea that perhaps
two or three inputs were most likely to
be related and then you started
looking for all the possibilities only
regarding those on chain i'm not well
it's not clear
guarantee is that the those links won't
be made
aren't we
i'm not sure that they're not any less
dangerous than input output links
because if i made a payment
with
uh one coin and then i made a different
payment with something that i got from
an exchange maybe i made a donation to
navalny's team in the us
and no value judgment on whether that's
good or not the putin regime wouldn't
like that if they saw that related to
kyc
account they'd be able to identify
that transaction with me if they could
make the link like these kind of dangers
are my concern and shipping this
software and i understand that we're all
striving for progress and there's no
perfect solution that exists yet but i
have to voice these concerns because
there are
real visceral human dangers
that we're trying to prevent yes but
the thing is basically right if you can
know
once in the blockchain that two inputs
are
related the only the only way you can
know that it's basically analyzing the
the coinjoin transaction right and
finding
all the possible
the compositions you don't need to find
all of them for the whole transaction
you just need to find all related to
that imp to those the inputs you're
interested in you you actually would
need to
if you wanted to if you wanted to
solidify that those two inputs are
linked you would need to find all if you
wanted to get a good approximation of
where the outputs are going then you're
correct you can
just target several inputs and assume
that they're from the same person assume
that there are no additional inputs and
say okay these inputs here with some
margin of error what are the likely
outputs and you will get a much reduced
set of outputs and there equal outputs
will defend the user as well as
different interpretations of the
of of the outputs but no if you think
two inputs are together you still need
all
combinations of inputs and outputs and
the subset sum problem to to
to say with confidence yes they are in
fact uh
you know
combined there's there's no way around
that
involving those inputs and outputs not
all of the ones where they're together
but just involving them if they're
totally involving something else
then what you have then what you have
when you get all of those involving
those two is you have
uh likely outputs that are linked to
those two inputs if those two inputs are
linked
it's not you you're not getting the the
fact that those two inputs are linked
like there is no targeted attack on two
specific inputs to get the link
between them themselves wasabi has more
exactly
that's awesome exactly
once once you find all the possible
decompositions in which those
inputs right participate you can say for
example okay
i found let's say
1 000 or 100 if you want okay i found
100 possible
sub transactions but it is because you
start from the from assuming the inputs
right
because you you say okay
because first you have to assume the
inputs but that is completely fake and
even if you say okay i want to see how
many sub transactions are possible with
this input so in the in that case you
are assuming the input you will find a
lot of some transactions so you have to
also assume the outputs and if you
assume the inputs and you assume the
output then it is a very very very
extremely biased
analysis in fact it's not an analysis
that is something that you try to
justify
your interpretation let's say but there
are many job execution though that's
that's what
we're trying to get people in trouble
too awesome so let me let me just um
kind of maybe summarize things um every
person that's done the sort of more
research side of wasabi has come to the
conclusions that there's a lot of
problems and that there are a lot of
dangers a lot of edge cases uh a lot of
concerns uh the best example is you've
all you've all uh you know was extremely
concerned about about things uh and then
i showed up a few months ago a
month and a half ago to to look at stuff
and then i i showed concerns so i i i
think
it's not that i'm telling you that
everything is without concerns it's the
opposite uh we
there's there's a lot of
stuff to do and and yes you know like
you know wasabi could go out and give
these like long caveats like you know if
you do this and then you do this and
then this happens and then your
particular concern is this then this is
what you should be worried about and you
should know this on the other hand
there's the fact that like what wallets
do people have as options when it comes
to privacy preserving wallets what
wallet would be like number two you know
there really isn't a lot to to go for
especially for like people who aren't
extremely tech oriented and can like
manage all their things and have like a
really in-depth stuff there's just this
unhappy i guess medium where we just
accept that there's there's like serious
problems we we live with them and we
think about them and and
and and and what you're saying where
like it's dangerous to ship this product
you're right it's dangerous to ship this
product it's also dangerous not to ship
this product right so you know what
would you do uh i mean delay it more
like i've i've been delaying i've been
begging people for this project sorry i
mean but but but i i think
that is not the the the way to
to go i mean
we have to to answer the question right
and
i know now i don't i don't know if i
really really really understand the
question that that that could be that
the first thing to clarify because
i need to understand this in order to
answer right so let me ask questions
right to understand the question what is
the difference i mean what why is in
this specific topic
why would be
a wabi-sabi a different
zero link or the the version one of
wasabi so why do you think that in this
case input
can be uh
linked by an external observer and yeah
and that was not possible in
in the previous version what what
changed in this regard i'm not asking
about any change i'm asking about the
security of the
product that's being released i don't
think there's any perfect solution that
exists right now
but but i mean you have a concern and i
i want to address your concept right so
i need to understand the question what
what lucas wants to know is is your
specific concern is that two inputs
could be linked because there's nothing
that inherently protects them when they
both register in a coin join right two
change in uh
outputs are now inputs in a coin join
you're concerned that they're linked
together that's that's the concern yeah
my concern is okay because it's knapsack
is this mitigated in the wasabi too or
not yet and it sounds like under some
circumstances if you do some analysis it
could be but it's not clear well just to
be clear lucas is very right about this
the analysis you need to do is the total
breakdown of a coin join which you know
once you get past like 120 inputs 120
outputs you now need special hardware
because for regular hardware it will
take you days
to to do this so once you get to you
know 200 input certain outputs it's it's
it's exponentially exponential
when when you look at the problem um so
it's you know
and all that gives you is the total
breakdown um which which again i
personally don't think it's it's very
plausible for more than a hundred and
you know 60 inputs 160 outputs um but
but that's just my you know
so so but you would need to do that to
to to get the the link between those
inputs and and it wouldn't tell you
those inputs are perfectly linked most
the time it would say that there's
there's a probabilistic link all inputs
and l outputs are linked to other inputs
and outputs by by some probability
just just to add this first of all it is
true that it is
really really really hard to find all
the sub transactions because it is
it grows the difficulty grows
exponentially but that is not
the
what guarantees that this car
if you for example analyze much much
smaller transaction right you try to
find all the possible decomposition for
a four input and four output
transactions you will find that there
are a lot
if you use a standard denominations
right basically the thing is that after
you found after you find all the
possible sub-transactions all the that
are at the order of i don't know i
should do the the numbers again i don't
remember but it have to be billions
right okay now you have to
filter right those uh sub transactions
that are using coin that you are
interested on right then you have all
the possible sub transactions in which
that specific coin can participate and
you can see
all that those substance sub
transactions contains multiple inputs so
probabilistically you say okay
there are there are this coin can be
probabilistically linked to this input
to this input to this input to the
symbol right what the chances well
are very very very small because the
number of sub transactions are huge
but to simplify to simplify this
explanation because it sounds like i
mean it is objectively true but
to make it even more simple right it is
exactly the same that you have to do
to
know the links in whatsapp you call it
one
it's exactly exactly the same right what
is the difference well in wasabi wallet
one you know
that the
a user can participate with up to seven
coins so you can let's say
narrow the the scope of your your
analysis to find all the possible
sub-transactions that have no more than
seven coins right so you can you you can
say okay these are all the
sub-transactions that contains more than
seven coins are not possible in the
solid so because you
the result of your analysis is better
right in what's happening two that is
not possible you don't know if the
user is participating with one coin
three coins seven coins fifty coins
right so you have to take all the
possibilities into accounts are really
really really in the order of
billions and billions you know so
how
probably is to link inputs
i think that is not what
juval was talking about
was talking about is what if the
coordinator
can perform some
kind of something that is what i think
but
on the blockchain is it's not so easy
okay thanks for answering guys well has
anyone else any questions
well i guess while we are waiting for
the
for the questions in the live chat
maybe max you could continue asking the
people around here about what were their
experiences
i was acting pretty cool
effect
let me let me ask jose if you are here
because i think you are the
you are the newest
you're the newest person
here the newest developer
so
what was your impression of the female
and everything that's going on here so
far
well
it's a
wonderful
environment uh to be honest
i haven't had
such a soft landing in my developer life
so
i'm very very very happy to be part of
your project
and in fact i'm very happy because
uh one of the features
wasabi 2.0 has is the search bar as you
may already know
and it's a
an insta interesting feature i'm very
happy with it it fulfilled me with
happiness
uh to see the feature in the release
so i can be
happier
to see that
included as part of the release
moreover i'm very happy to be
around with such a wonderful people
so
because
an old an old one
i'm already 41
and
it's it's
it's incredible
how you
uh
guys
get everything over
and how you
realize of minor issues even
you have a
a feeling of perfection
and that's
really really important
this is top quality product
i haven't filled this in other open
source projects
and finally it's it's a quality thing i
think
taking everything as a whole
wasabi is is a
great place to to work in
and i'm really proud of it and that's it
i think i cannot
say anything than
good works good words and good quirk
everyone
uh congratulate everyone here yeah and
actually your the search bar that you
implemented is a perfect example of what
i mentioned earlier that this is a
really cool feature um and it's very
useful already as it is but you know he
even had that pr that uh includes to
search for example for transaction id
and address and stuff like this but
that's just a glimpse of the potential
that we have now um that where we can
further refine the wallet experience
tremendously you know like a feature
like is this andrew's mind just paste
something in and shows you which wallet
it belongs to and the details associated
with it
that's really powerful and it's great to
see that we we have those basic
foundations in this release but yeah
there's it's just one example of many of
how much more potential there is
in many different aspects so yeah things
will say for making that search bar
happen it's a pretty cool feature it's a
pleasure
marnix how about you
what have you been tinkering on uh
you're also
a newer contributor to the project and
you've grown and contributed in quite a
couple different areas so what was your
experience like
hey
yes been quite a ride looking forward to
this day everyone of course for
two years plus finally happened and
even this is just the beginning of a
wasabi 2.0 of course and
yeah let's see but we have already come
far and it's an awesome project the
wallet is great and super happy that the
day is finally here
let me just mention someone who could
not be here
who
was
the person who
created most of the ui stuff for wasabi
at 1.2 and now with the team with wasabi
2.0 and it's dan ramsey he's a
maintainer of avalonia the ui framework
wasabi is using and he's actually having
another child today a riva not only was
available at 1.2 turns out this was the
day
when he or she was born so i just wanted
to congratulate him for that
likewise and uh he's been doing really
awesome work that's one of the things i
mentioned earlier where we were shifting
gold gold posts uh throughout the
progress and we started out with hey
let's just you know
upgrade the avalonia back end and make
the exact same user interface you know
some minor changes but nothing much
and all of a sudden oh how about we do
it completely from scratch
uh but uh that yeah turned into a
behemoth work
but then managed it uh excellently
and also here to mention just that
collaboration of the wasabi team and the
avalonia
framework like the upstream
contributions uh that that we make and
the help that we get from upstream to
make wasabi better is is just insanely
awesome that's one of the my favorite
parts of the software of how we
collaborate with upstream dependencies
and then is doing an awesome job of
standing there on both sides and being
that link to make sure it works as good
as it does now
that's that's super valuable yeah he you
know and he he called it basically by
himself uh the
first 1.0
wasabi gui you know just before breaking
bitcoin and lisbon yeah he basically
rockstar did in in a couple days or
weeks and now it took him two years
to do it this time
and a bunch of more cold monkeys to help
along but ultimately i think the the
difference shows and this is quite slick
and robust but again lots of potential
uh it's far from perfect we have a bunch
of work to do to make it even better and
we also have el sileon in the chat
um he is working on some other awesome
charmian e cash or well e-cash magic and
that's federated e-cash for money
warehouses with ready mint so i'm siri
and what's up hey sorry for being late
uh but didn't want to miss
release
i've been waiting for it for a long time
and really happy that it's finally out
so uh next challenge is probably getting
it to run on nixos
as
always yes indeed not a supported
operating system but would be cool if we
can make that happen you know
in general
there is a
someone that created a package for for
wasabi
that's that would be awesome
it is available in fact i have if we
could do you think and
i don't think so no but but anyway as i
told you i i use xos so it's it works
perfectly right
the only the only thing is that i i i
use my
i mean or you or you patch the door or
use the the install
from from links but that is the only
thing basically that
have to change is
it worked perfectly
yeah that sounds awesome and looking
forward to building a next generation so
i can try it out and probably not
environment
as you always do when you don't know how
to get something to run
uh and you know nixon is used on a lot
of uh servers and
the kind of headless wasabi server uh
with a rpc server interface you know
the rudiments of it are there but again
it's far from being perfect and we
didn't really spend much time on it
before this release uh however i think
it's a bunch of people are interested in
making that a lot better so i'm hoping
that the future work here will make the
life of atlas server operators a lot
better including xos yeah it would be an
awesome addition to next bitcoin
yeah yeah we talked about this a while
ago already and one of the big problems
for example was that uh the you could
not generate a new wallet exclusively in
the headless demon uh because of some
yeah weird architecture quirks so stuff
like this was always a bit of a handicap
and i'm not sure how much of that is
fixed
but yeah they're workarounds um but
hopefully it's going to be more pretty
in the future but kik zuma has something
to say yeah i wanted to ask if there is
any road map or if there is any priority
or whatever about this topic so so i i
would like to have an idea like when
it could possibly be viable well that's
a super good question you know to be
honest for a large extent we were kind
of heads down preparing this release and
we'll have to take a breath and
reevaluate now afterwards uh of what
should be the future priorities but
at least for me personally having a good
headless experience is
and a good rpc server is going to be
overall very important i
would like if someone could do the work
just you know unfortunately i'm not the
dictator of the free software project so
it's tough to coordinate people as usual
but i know that lucas is also interested
in this to at least some extent but he's
also interested in a bunch of other
topics so yeah
to be honest really tough to say about
the roadmap right now other than we have
a bunch of ideas and it's going to be
super difficult to prioritize on which
ones we should focus on we have a bunch
of ideas i've been working on what comes
after wasabi 2.2
and of course there is no root one but
what i was trying to do is that i am
trying to collect the ideas
and somehow organize them into a
coherent representation of them and i
came up with three categories one would
be maintenance the other scaling and the
third is innovation regarding
maintenance it's uh it's not only just
maintenance it's improving the existing
things right that's uh that's where we
will have to pay a lot of attention in
the future but other than that uh as we
are growing we are able to
get into different things and and that's
when scaling and innovation comes in now
in the innovation part that's what all
we've been doing so far with with wasabi
well that we were trying to make
non-incremental meaningful significant
improvements
based on a lot of research
and now i believe we came to a point
where significant improvements
would be
only possible
if we could involve the lightning
network because in a in a high level the
only issue left is that people who have
low amount of volume in their bullet
it's going to be expensive maybe not
today but
you know how do you scale a blockchain
you don't
so
eventually it is going to get more and
more expensive for low volume people and
that's when the lighting network comes
in and that's most likely is the future
at this point i think we can say that
so
we started the lightning network
research grant where we are
trying to design uh privacy
oriented but we gave out as a task
research task to design privacy
guarantees for lightning network or or
or do anything
with that right like maybe just do a
survey on on hey how private is
lightning network because at this point
there are a lot of questions but anyhow
that's uh that's the direction we
started going
and finally the spelling part which is
going to be the next step and scaling
means we should enable the usage of
mastabi for more type of users
for example there are four four main
things actually but for example
one of the
the thing is that well guess what not
everyone speaks english
so it would be good to have a
localization so that might be the next
thing we are working on it's it's not
probably not as large as the job as the
rest but that i'm
talking about the other ones are going
to other platforms maybe mobile or
or
hardware
native hardware but coinjoin integration
so currently people cannot do hardware
well let's speed with coin joints
that uh cannot do coinjs without levels
so so that's uh that's that would be
quite cool if we could uh right because
that's that's a safer way to to store
your volume having it in a hardware
wallet rather than in a hot wallet right
like in wasabi right now and the final
category which
brings back to your question would be
the developer tools so there are
projects those are interested in in
using wasabi balance among some jinkies
there is pure here
so we would like to make make things
easier for for them and one of the way
to make things easier for
for integrating hospital that would be
rpc and demand and bad documented
nice user guides maybe even video guides
and tutorials good project sorry yes
right like that would be the ideal way
to to go about that so so that's when
where it comes in as you can see this is
the headless mood of pasta
is certainly in the bucket of ideas that
might come next but
but we did not decide yet we don't have
a roadmap it's a it's just an ideas
yeah it's coming in two weeks
i mean maybe a question for you el
sirion uh like your your work on the
charmian e cash bank is quite nice
uh and
i i wonder how you would uh like how you
currently deal with unchained privacy
for your federation uh and you know how
coinjoin might help you in the future
that's actually a great question i
currently we don't deal with that at all
because
right now federated ecash is only a
privacy
means to gain privacy for users
and users don't really have to think
about
like the utxos of the federation all
that much because their main way of
interacting with the federation is
through lightning and there they already
have pretty good privacy properties
because whenever they
send or receive on lightning
the other side is uh ecash and ecash has
like the best privacy you can get
essentially like um
you should have
like pull anonymity for the sender or
recipient um on the cash side
respectively like the main problem
currently we're thinking about is
lighting privacy so for example
if you're sending money
to some other lighting node then you
generally leak
their
node id
and so while you don't leak who is the
sender you leak something about the
recipient which might in turn leak
something about the sender again
like there are these complicated uh
problems that like if there's anything
that's being leaked then it might be in
relation
to
like the user who
is using ecash and does everything right
but
like if the other side like something
that's a problem so on chain like in the
long term what i'd wish for is that all
these layer two and layer three
solutions like for example federated
ecacas are also like
liquid other federations like bigger
custodians like
single users
that
they in the long term will use
a utex oath of common denominations like
that's what you're already doing with
wabi zabi or wasabi 2.0
and you have a bunch of common
denominations that users
can use to create utex os in and then
you can spend them
again but like currently when you want
to like pay
for goods and services on chain
you need to grind down these common
denominations because they typically
don't fit exactly what you want to pay
but in the future i imagine like most of
the commerce moves
into the upper layers like your actual
day-to-day uh transferring of money
moves to lightning moves to federate the
ecash
and so what you can do on chain is you
only send common denominations and
once we hit that point that nobody does
arbitrary denomination utxos anymore
like most people don't
then coinjoins would be so much more
powerful
because suddenly
you don't have any toxic change anymore
you just create a big coin joint that
takes like common denominations as
inputs and common denominations as
outputs
and maybe you add some mutex o for fees
that uh is not of a common denomination
because you have to remove a little bit
for peace but in general you would just
recycle
like common denomination you take so's
and just keep them in these
denominations
making coin joints much more efficient
and like that's the future i hope for
with bitcoin
and i hope that rabi zabi it's a great
protocol like um
the ecash
part makes it very resilient against
all kinds of like de-anonymization
attacks like it's the gold standard
essentially when it comes to a privacy
and if we figure some things out on the
coin selection side like which
denominations we choose then i think
this can be a protocol
that we use for many many
years or decades
so really looking forward to that future
yeah nice that's really awesome to hear
one thing that i'd also like to bring up
is that i think there is a possibility
that wasabi could make great use of
something like vetiment
because i do believe that
it it might make sense to have some
custodial layer with cheap and small
value payments to help alleviate some of
the problems in the coin join um
and yeah i think that i mean either that
custodial bank can use the wabi-sabi
anonymous credentials
as a centralized money warehouse or of
course fedement comes in with a
decentralized money warehouse in a
federation
and
but in general the idea might be
interesting um but yeah yeah i think
they're
indeed very complementary in nature like
for big amounts uh barbie's ib is still
the way to go or like coin joints in
general
because like you don't want to trust the
federation with like hundreds of your
bitcoins and it probably wouldn't be a
a good way to mix anyway because the
federation might not be big enough
or it doesn't have enough throughput
enough flow and you can probably achieve
much higher flow with coinjoins because
people don't have to trust like the
coordinator it's trustless
and on the other hand if you do small
payments then as you said like it makes
much more sense to trust such entity or
no power i mentioned it like we have to
find ways to make private payments
viable
that's i think where minimum comes in
and where it can help enormously and
then there's also like this in between
like when you pay on chain today after
coinjoining with wasabi then you get
like these comedy nominations and when
you spend you get some change and what
do you do with the change like you have
to get it into some common denomination
again
and you will probably get some amount of
change from that
and
like traditionally like maybe it's not
as big of a problem anymore because now
you can just use the change to pay for
peace or whatever like your common
denominations are small enough but what
you could also do is instead of
generating like really small utxos you
just send this change to federation and
then after you accumulate a bit of such
change then you
withdraw
like a bigger common denomination you
take so again like you do this for a
month or so and then you have like 0.1
bitcoin again accumulated you withdraw
it and can do coin joints with this
again
because it already has the common
denomination which is great yes exactly
and just on in a bit more for the coin
joint service could be improved with
ecash
like money
ecash is that for example right if you
have these standard denominations let's
say exactly 1.00 bitcoin then you might
want to register exactly 1.00 bitcoin on
the output side but the big question of
course how are you going to pay for
mining fees and and here
the current solution is just register
more inputs basically
but of course the alternative would be
pay
somehow the coordinator or
another third-party service provider
to pay for the binding fee
by including his own inputs
um and that can be done via lightning
that can be done via
e-cash payments or mini mint
uh and i think that yeah that's that's
enough benefit for both yeah i think
that's a great vision because adding out
inputs for fees is just a wasteful
and if you already have like common
denomination inputs
and you can just get them out the same
size again then
it makes so much sense just to pay
someone to add their utics o for fees
and i really hope that there's will be
more work into that direction
yeah it's very great anyone has any
other
ideas or thoughts or comments
maybe the office could give us a
situation on updates like what's going
on
is there some news yes how drunk are you
did more champions champagne bottles pop
what time
it was something
getting back into reality the the path
actually and
getting us back to the reality however
adam is an euphoric laugh
whenever he
see the gif because there is already a
gift
about that
so
the the number of downloads is 189
currently and the first coin joy around
will be there in 18 minutes but only if
we reach the input number of 150 so we
will see
if that's gonna happen the
the number is a bit high i mean the
minimum required number of inputs is a
bit high if you compare for example the
number of downloads
it's almost the same and whoever
download the software it is not
deterministic that he will go and join
as well
so
probably the first round
uh we'll retry
but we previously at least if you know
how we are standing there because when
the coordinator we restart the round
then we will know what was the
the actual number of inputs at that
point
yeah the last i know of is uh input
registration count of 22
that was like 10 minutes ago or
something so probably more by now but
probably not enough to trigger the first
round yet
and in this case if i understand it
correctly we go we abandon this current
round and go into a new round a new
input registration where uh anyone can
register again
kik sunil you have here something on
your mind what's up
so there was discussion about uh
integrating lightning i wonder if
there are any plans for zetka snakes to
also provide like lightning service
lighting services like uh some opero
mobile wallets do or if there is idea to
just
make it available and let people connect
to their own
nodes i mean not their own but
to the nodes they select themselves
at the random or
based on some recommendation or whatever
that's a really good question
and in general it's
it's definitely something that we're
looking into because lightning service
providers are another great bitcoin
native business model alongside two
conjoined coordination
um
of course different in many aspects if
we actually end up doing it
i guess depends on the research that
we're doing right now
because if we find that we can have a
lightweight private by default wallet
experience or architecture without any
third-party service providers well then
we will probably do that
um however i'm thinking and that's just
an intuition is that a service provider
will alleviate a lot of problems and
frictions
in lightning
and then the big question is can we
design a protocol for this lightning
service provider to perform the service
in
the in in the most privacy optimized way
and you know here are things like ck
channels or
you know maybe coordinated channel
factories or stuff like this yeah lots
of possible things you know maybe some
blinded
route path calculations or
what whatever might be possible and to
be honest i don't know about all half of
these so we
we will see if it's necessary and if
we're able to provide a useful service
according to our privacy ethos and in
any case
it's a long way out so it'll come to you
in two weeks of course yeah one of the
things i had in mind is maybe it could
be
combinable if uh coinjoin
so for instance it could be a way of
dealing with
change outputs so you could conjoin and
put the change directly into lightning
channel that is opened with case next
which provides a way to then like mix up
the amount especially if this was
implemented on top of taproot it it
would actually
improve privacy even of those people who
don't do this
yeah for sure
and again maybe we can do even better
right and get some block space
efficiencies by something like a
private channel factory uh and that is
of course great for for conjoined
coordinator because the channel factory
after all is just a coin join of many
users opening a channel in single output
um but yeah that also also the these
whole
coin swaps and lightning channels and
stuff like this they as you say
increase the subset ambiguity of every
calendar and participant even if they
don't use these fancy second layer magic
especially if temperatures involved so
uh yeah it's it's a big idea it's it's a
lot of work
so we will consider again there's so
much to do right these are all awesome
ideas the questions just which of them
do we tackle first and that's just yeah
super difficult
but that's why feedback rounds like this
are super important right because we see
what what you guys think are uh is
important to tackle next
adam do you have anything else to bring
up
no i'm good
anyone uh is there any marketing on like
reddit i know there was like a tweet
that went out but are there any other
like campaigns right now to get some
early liquidity in
i think there is did not yet confirm but
there should be so there's like a reddit
post somewhere about this i believe yes
there's also a blog post on blog.wasabi
io and it's reddit.com
ce slash wasabi wallet or something like
that okay so i see a uh i see a post
from four minutes ago yahia posted you
see that synchronicity
at least someone is working here
all right fellas if there's nothing else
to discuss i would say let's conclude uh
this wasabi wallet 2.0 release
livestream party uh was nice to get
everyone
involved with sharing a bit of the story
of how we got to this point and thanks
for the people joining uh with some nice
questions
um we keep it coming
we're happy for feedback let us know
what you think of the new wallet the new
user interface the new conjoined
functionality
and let's see how we can make wasabi 2.0
even better in the upcoming versions
uh there is a lot of room uh to do that
so i'm eager for all the future
contributions and quite bullish on what
we're about to build if you got any
final words
um please do otherwise we'll end the
stream
bitcoin to the moon
privacy by default
2.0 to the moon
if you open a champagne always make sure
you don't have anything
above you or put your thumb on top of
the cork
don't put the cat in the microwave
[Music]
for whatever you want
bitcoin
[Music]
improve your is
build your dreams
care for yourself
[Music]
find your love
develop your ideas
[Music]
bitcoin is the future
but is visible to all
your transactions are your business
reclaim your privacy
[Music]